# **Adu Matory**

adu@adumatory.com Github | LinkedIn www.adumatory.com I am a data scientist with 7+ years of research and software development experience in healthcare. I specialize in neurocognitive biomarker discovery, data strategy, and advanced statistical modeling. I'm skilled at project management, experimental study design, and exploring new technologies to drive the development of mental health services.

### **NOTABLE PROJECTS**

Digital Therapeutics Platform for Psychotherapy, at Cybin Inc. (2021 - 2022)

Patients often struggle to transform motivation found during therapy sessions into behavioral change in their everyday lives. I **invented a ML signal processing algorithm** that uses data from **multiple devices to facilitate treatment and evaluate patient outcomes**. I led the project through proof-of-concept, coordinating an international team in Europe, North America and Southeast Asia, and **co-authored a patent** for its use in psychotherapy, adding a 13<sup>th</sup> patent to the IP of a growing NYSE-traded startup.

Finding Neural Correlates of Personality, at Charité Medical University (2019 - 2020)

Associated with mental disorder severity, personality type is rarely leveraged in psychiatric treatments. A better understanding of its neural basis might be used to improve and personalize clinical care. I **built an open-source application that automates training and comparison of ML and deep learning models** that predict personality type from a **17TB fMRI dataset**. Researchers with little mathematical knowledge can easily find optimal training parameters, explore neural correlates, cluster personality subtypes, and visualize results, furthering their search for reliable neural predictors of psychiatric disease.

### WORK EXPERIENCE

## **Data Scientist, Wearable Tech and Neural Data**

Jul 2021 - Jun 2022

Cybin Inc.

- First in-house Data Scientist and **lead engineer of a biosignal analysis pipeline for a digital platform**. Vetted proposed partnerships with 17 tech companies, **led a team of 15+ engineers and developers** to create AWS-hosted app, and designed a study to evaluate usability of the user interface and gameified features.
- Interviewed internal teams (Clinical, Operations, R&D, Innovation) about their data use cases and **architected solutions for a company-wide data ecosystem** and data governance policies that optimized data integrity and stakeholder accessibility to key insights in a biotech development environment.

# Research Assistant, Connectomics for Psychiatry

Sep 2019 - Dec 2020

Research Division of Mind and Brain, Charité Medical University of Berlin

- Sole engineer of an application designed to **investigate brain-biomarkers of clinically relevant psychometrics**, like intelligence and personality. Implemented differential geometry and graph theoretical analyses to extract features from multimodal (e.g. demographic, fMRI) data. Using PyTorch and xarray, **created a novel method of prediction using multitask fMRI data** to train Convolutional Neural Networks and Gaussian mixture models.
- Sharing data and results with other psychiatry working groups, identified new directions for research and organized a conference featuring presenters from University of Oxford.

# Research Intern, Altered States of Consciousness

May 2020 - Sep 2020

Neurocomputation and Neuroimaging Unit, Freie University of Berlin

- Conducted a pilot experiment to investigate the effect of personal electroencephalographic (EEG) signatures and stimulation frequency on hallucinations. Collected subjects' data, created a database using xarray, and used NumPy and MNE to identify functional neural activity associated with visual hallucinations and potential targets for intervention in schizophrenia and psychedelic therapies.
- Discovered preliminary evidence that reduced connectivity between select brain regions may lead to simple visual hallucinations and applied for a grant to further research their underlying neural mechanisms. **Awarded the 2020 Source Award**, the top-tier research grant from the Source Research Foundation.

### Research Intern, Perceptual Bias in Graphic Design

Aug 2019 - Nov 2019

Active Perception and Cognition Lab, Humboldt University of Berlin

- Ran a study using a **new approach to empirically identify best practices in visual design** and determine the the efficacy of traditional heuristics in visual communication. **Modeled behavioral data** with regression and Bayesian hierarchical models in R's RStan and Ime, identifying visualization methods that optimize intuitive understanding of the underlying data.
- Implemented an approach to benchmark various algorithms, using R's maxLik package, leading to a 5x performance boost in computational usage and processing time, enabling my team to save several hours each week and increasing the speed that they could innovate through model experimentation.

Neurological Intensive Care Unit, Columbia University Medical Center

• Coordinator of 14 research studies on experimental therapies and outcome prediction for neurological disorders, including feasibility studies for the use of brain-computer interfaces for patient pain management. Project-managed a team of 50 physicians, technicians, and nurses in the collection of lab, neuroimaging, and EMR data

### **SOFTWARE**

# Languages

Python Machine Learning (PyTorch, Tensorflow, Keras, Data Manipulation (dplyr), Visualization Scikit-Learn, lightgbm), Data Manipulation (ggplot2), Modeling (lme4, Rstan, maxLik) **MATLAB** (NumPy, Pandas, xarray), Visualization Neuroimaging Analysis (FieldTrip, Chronux) (matplotlib, WandB), Mathematical Optimization LaTeX Typesetting (amsmath, apacite, mathtools) (bayesian-optimization, PuLP), Modeling (MNE, JavaScript **Bootstrap** NetworkX, NLTK) **HTML CSS** Bash

Version Control Git, Travis CI Development Frameworks Scrum, Kanban Architectural Patterns ETL, MVC, E-R Databases for Business (AWS, SQLite, Microsoft Office), for Research (Redcap), EMRs (Natus, Eclipsys)

#### **PATENTS**

Matory, A; Greene, B. Integrated Data Collection Devices for Use in Psychotherapy. U.S. Patent Provisional.

### **PUBLICATIONS & PRESENTATIONS**

6 peer-reviewed publications/conference presentations. See my [Google Scholar profile] for further details.

# **EDUCATION**

## **Computational Neuroscience MSc**

Technische Universität - Berlin, Germany

I applied machine learning, Bayesian methods, and biophysical models to many collaborative software development projects **modeling neural, cognitive, and behavioral processes**. I **published my master's thesis**, an analysis of failing organ systems during cardiac death, raising ethical considerations about death diagnosis and organ donation.

# **Psychology BA**

New York University - New York, NY, USA

During a **one-year internship with NYU Langone's psilocybin-assisted psychotherapy research group**, I screened patients for study eligibility and managed study data integrity. For my thesis, I designed a study proposal to investigate the relationship between feelings of unity and craving in patients with alcohol use disorder.

# AWARDS

Grant for the start or completion of studies (2021), studierendenWERK Berlin

## Source Award (2020), Source Research Foundation

The top-tier research grant, to further study the neural mechanisms of visual hallucinations

Clinical Research Coordinator of Excellence (2018), Columbia University Medical Center

Excellence in Programming Award (2016), New York University Global Spiritual Life
For outstanding event coordination during NYU's Refugee Awareness Week

# LANGUAGES

English (Native), German (Business-fluent), Spanish (Business-fluent)